Guide to the Hugo Leander Blomquist papers, 1927-1961
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Hugo Leander Blomquist papers 1927-1961
University Archives, Duke University
Blomquist, Hugo Leander, 1885-1964.
4.8 Linear Feet 3000 Items
Hugo Leander Blomquist was professor and chair of the Botany Department at Duke University from 1921-1957.
The collection includes correspondence, class notes, North Carolina maps, as well as drawings and photographs of his book The Grasses of North Carolina. The collection ranges in date from 1927-1961.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
Provenance
The Hugo Leander Blomquist papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1977-1978; 2007.
Biographical Note
Hugo Leander Blomquist was born in Sorsele, Sweden in 1888 and moved with his parents to Kulm, North Dakota in 1892. He grew up on the family farm and attended public schools in North Dakota before attending the University of Chicago, where he received his B.S. in 1916. He took two years off in the middle of his undergraduate career to serve as principal of a high school in Deering, ND. From 1917 to 1919 he served as musician first class in the U.S. Army overseas; after the war, he stayed in Paris to study biological chemistry at the Pasteur Institute. When he returned to the U.S., he enrolled in the graduate program in botany at the University of Chicago, and earned his Ph.D. in 1921.
Blomquist joined the faculty at Trinity College in 1921 in the Department of Biology, specializing in fungi, algae, vascular plants and bacteriology. In 1935, when the Biology Department split into divisions of zoology and botany, Blomquist became Chair of the Botany Department. He retired in 1957.
Among Blomquist's publications include A Guide to the Spring and Early Summer Flora of the Piedmont, North Carolina, Flowers of the South, Native and Exotic, The Grasses of North Carolina, Hepaticae of North Carolina, Ferns of North Carolina and Vascular Anatomy of Angiopteris Evecta.
Collection Overview
Collection contains personal and professional correspondence of Hugo L. Blomquist from the years 1927 to 1961. Also includes maps, notes and oversize illustrations and photographs associated with the publication of his book Grasses of North Carolina. Illustrations were removed from acidic paper wrapping and boxed for preservation.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Faculty
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History -- 20th century
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University. Dept. of Botany
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Related Material
Dept. of Botany Records
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
Kramer (Paul J.) Papers, 1856-1994 (bulk 1927-1974)
Duke University Archives
Oosting (Henry J.) Papers, 1937-1968
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Accessions A77-220, A78-145
  - Correspondence, 1927-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950
  - Correspondence, 1951
  - Correspondence, 1952
  - Correspondence, 1953
  - Correspondence, 1954-1961, undated
  - Blomquist/UNC Press Correspondence, 1952 January-1954 January (Box 2)
  - Notes and Outlines
  - Identification of Grasses by Their Vegetative Characters, Notes and Outlines
  - NC Maps (1 of 5)
  - NC Maps (2 of 5)
  - NC Maps (3 of 5)
  - NC Maps (4 of 5)
  - NC Maps (5 of 5)
  - The Grasses of North Carolina
  - Illustrations and Photographs for Blomquist's The Grasses of North Carolina (Box 3)
- Accession UA2007-0041, 2 Boxes
  This accession is unprocessed. Patrons should contact University Archives staff in advance if use of these materials is desired.